[Music]
What happens when someone inside the
intelligence machine decides to tell the
truth? When the cost of conscious is
prison, but the reward is clarity for
the rest of us. Today on Unfiltered with
Sam, we're diving deep into the dark
underbelly of uh US intelligence. from
torture programs to the wars that were
built on lies. We'll explore why
whistleblowers are punished while war
criminals walk free and who these
institutions truly serve, the people or
power itself. My guest today knows the
answer from the inside and frankly he
needs no introductions. John Kiriago is
a CIA officer turned whistleblower.
During uh his uh time at the agency, he
held senior roles including executive
assistant to the deputy director. After
911, John led counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan and was
responsible for the capture of Abu
Zubeda, who at the time was believed to
be one of the top three figures in
al-Qaeda. In 2007, John became the first
US official to publicly confirm the
CIA's use of torture, blowing the
whistle on the Bush administration's
enhanced interrogation program. Though
cleared of espionage, he was later
prosecuted for uh allegedly disclosing
classified information to journalists
and served 30 months in prison. After
leaving the agency, John also served as
a senior investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee under
Senator John Kerry. You can follow his
work on uh on his personal handles and
on his own website. I'm going to include
uh links to those in the description box
below. So, John, welcome to Unfiltered
the Sam. Thank you so much for having
me.
It's a pleasure to have you to host you
and uh I'm glad we're uh finally uh
touching base. So, I'd like to start I'd
like to start at the heart of it all.
The moment when your name stopped being
just another agency file and became a
symbol of uh truthtelling in a system
built on uh
secrecy. So, uh, my question actually is
that the cost you you you served
slightly more than two years in prison
for allegedly disclosing the identity
of,
um,
of a covered CIA officer to a journalist
in violation of the Intelligence
Protections uh, act where you have
consistently maintained that your
prosecution was politically motivated to
uh, for exposing the CIA's use of uh,
uh, waterboarding. and other enhanced
interrogation um techniques. In fact,
you're the only CIA officer jailed in
connection with the post 911 torture
program. Correct. Not for participating
in carrying out the torture, but for
exposing it and still your record hasn't
been clear, John. Meanwhile, the
architects of torture live with impunity
and a presidential pardon remains out of
reach. What does it say about the US
justice system, Joe, that the truth
teller lives with a felony while the
architects of torture live within
impunity?
Uh, thank you for that question. Um,
that's one of the sad things that we
have to live with in the justice system
that we've given ourselves. I wish that
I could say that I was alone uh in that
description that you just gave, but I'm
not alone. Between passage of the
Espionage Act in
1917 and the election of Barack Obama as
president in 2009, three Americans were
charged with espionage for uh speaking
with the media about waste, fraud,
abuse, or illegality, whistleblowing.
Just in the eight years that Barack
Obama was president, eight of us were
arrested and charged with espionage for
blowing the whistle on wrongdoing in the
intelligence community. And that has
continued on under Donald Trump. So I
think it says that that our government
here is not really concerned about
truth. It's not concerned about the rule
of law, despite what it says in
public despite what it says at the
United Nations or at political
conventions. It's more concerned about
maintaining what Donald Trump has lately
called the blob or the deep state as the
status quo.
You know, we we tell countries all all
the time that we are governed by the
rule of law here in the United States
and that we want other countries to adop
adopt the rule of law and adapt to its
use every day. We don't do that. It's
very hypocritical for us to tell
countries to live the way we live and
then and then just pretend that we live
right. It's not it's it's not the way to
run a society.
But what does it say to those still
inside, John? I mean, you've talked
about how uh whistleblowers like Edward
Snowden can't get a fair trial under the
Espionage Act, especially in places like
the Eastern District of Virginia. But
beyond the legal trap, what does that do
morally to people inside the system who
who really do want to serve the system?
Those who see wrongdoing but know the
cost of conscience is annihilation, just
like what they did with you.
Yeah, the the message is loud and clear
and the message is keep your mouth shut.
If you are a witness to waste, fraud,
abuse, illegality, or threats to the
public health or public
safety, in public, they'll say you have
to report it. You have to go through the
chain of command. You have to go to the
inspector general. You have to go to the
congressional oversight committees. In
reality, the only thing you can do is
keep your mouth shut because
otherwise your life will be upended. Let
me give you as one example Thomas Drake
from NSA, the National Security
Agency. Thomas Drake
saw crystal clear evidence that NSA was
spying on American citizens in the
aftermath of the 9/11 attacks. It is
against the law for NSA to spy on
Americans. It is a violation of NSA's
charter to spy on Americans. So Tom
Drake did exactly as he was supposed to
do. He went to his supervisor. He went
to the uh to the inspector general. He
went to the general counsel. He went to
the Pentagon inspector general. And then
he went to the congressional oversight
committee. Everybody that he reported
this to was cleared for the information.
Yet he was charged with seven counts of
espionage and two counts of theft of
government property. The property being
the information that he walked out of
the building with in his head. Now that
case fell apart and the charges were
dropped, but not until he was fired. He
lost his security clearance. He lost his
pension. He lost his wife and children.
lost his house and ended up working the
next 8 years at an Apple store here in
the Washington area.
So sad. So sad. And terrible. I I mean I
happen to I've mentioned Edward Snowden.
I mean do do you do you have a way are
you in touch with him? What's happening
with him? Yes. Is he eventually in a
good state?
You know, he told me in January of 2020
that the thing that he worried about the
most was he had a fear of becoming
irrelevant.
And I'm I'm sorry to say I think he's
gotten to that point where he's
irrelevant. He blew the whistle 12 years
ago. Yeah.
He told us 12 years ago that the
American government was spying on
American citizens and that they were
they had infiltrated every aspect of our
lives and nothing has changed. Congress
hasn't acted on his information. I'm
glad we have the information, but we're
we're no more secure now than we were 12
years ago when he first told us about
it.
So I I worry that as in the case of
Snowden, who at least was able to escape
with his freedom, Yeah. anybody else who
is in a position to blow the whistle
looks at cases like Snowden and Tom
Drake and John Kuryaku and just says
it's not worth it. And I'll add one
other thing, too. After the Snowden
revelations, the CIA implemented two new
programs in CIA headquarters. First of
all, they loaded new software through
the entire CIA computer system where the
computer can detect if a user may be
thinking about blowing the whistle and
it will report you to CIA security
before you've even said a
word. Number one. Number two, there is
now a reward system at the CIA. If you
report on your co-workers, oh wow, oh, I
think I think John is going to be a
whistleblower. And then they take my
badge, they escort me out of the
building, and they fire me and you get
an award.
Very very
difficult culture that we have in the
American intelligence uh community. And
now it's a culture of like uh you know
Stalinist Soviet Union. Yeah. Where you
have to genuinely worry that the people
that you work with are going to rat you
out or maybe make something up if they
see you as a professional threat.
I mean u it used to be a time when uh uh
people would uh want to contribute and
and be hired by the CIA and felt really
really proud of it and patriotic about
it. Now it's a completely different
narrative. I I assume
it really is. I It's I wonder why people
in general though are complacent to all
these all the revelations that have come
out about them being spied on. Why are
the people in mass complacent though?
Why? I think for a couple of reasons. I
think that number one, they just
automatically assume that the government
is is spying on us anyway. And you know
that old rhetorical question from Joseph
Gerbles in the 1930s, if you're doing
nothing wrong, then why do you care?
That's what that's what they keep
saying. Yeah. And and I think
that I think that beginning with the
George W. Bush
administration, successive White Houses
have so frightened the American people
that we are one bad decision away from
another massive terrorist attack. that
most Americans have been willing to give
up their civil rights and civil
liberties in exchange for this elusive
thing that the government calls
security. And for me, and I know that
I'm in the minority uh on this issue, I
would rather risk another terrorist
attack than give up my
rights. I understand where you're coming
from. Let's let's get now into another
aspect of US intelligence.
Um, the US invaded Iraq based on what
turned out to be a lie that Saddam had
weapons of Oh, yeah. mass destruction.
That lie came straight from the CIA,
John, and the intelligence community.
But Iraq wasn't the first. Words have
repeatedly been justified with
manipulated intelligence. So why does
the system keep producing intel that
leads to war at the cost of continuously
destabilizing entire regions like mine?
Is it to serve the military industrial
complex that politicians rely on or to
serve priorities and interests of allies
like Israel? Because US intelligence
agencies are supposed to serve the
American people, aren't they?
That is a very important question and
the answer is
yes. I'm I'm joking, of course.
But so looking at it from the beginning,
from the Iraq war, it's it's a little
bit more complicated than your question
makes it seem in that I remember
knockdown dragout fights between CIA
analysts and Department of Energy
analysts about whether the Iraqis had
weapons of mass destruction. inside the
CIA. The final analytic
line was probably not. The Iraqis
probably did
not. The energy department said yes,
they did. That what they have is dual
use. And even if they say that they
don't have weapons of mass destruction,
they have the ability to create weapons
of mass destruction. And I remember one
of the explanations being, we all agree
there's no nuclear program. Everybody
agrees biological weapons. Nobody has
any idea because all you need to create
a biological weapon is a kitchen. It
really is that easy. Just a k just a
kitchen. Chemical weapons. That's where
the fight was. And that's and that's
where analysts disagreed based on the
age of the information. Now, keep in
mind that almost all of the intelligence
that was coming into the CIA was a lie.
And it was meant to be a lie
because because of one man named Ahmed
Chelabi. Ahmed Chelaby was an Iraqi
Kurd, a Shia Muslim, which is unusual
for Kurds, but he had his family had
moved to Jordan when he was a young boy.
He went to school in London, got a PhD,
and then founded a bank in uh Jordan
called Petra Bank. He ended up stealing
the life savings of every Iraqi in
Jordan who had money in that bank and he
escaped to London, allegedly in the
trunk of his secretary's car across the
border into
Syria. Um the CIA had a long and ugly
history with Ahmed Chelaby. He was a
liar. He was a thief. He was a con man.
And so the CIA issued something called a
burn notice against him. It was a a
cable to every CIA officer in the world
saying, "You are forbidden from speaking
with Ahmed Chelby. He has stolen
millions of dollars of our money. He
tells us lies every time we speak to
him. Nobody is allowed to have any
contact with him." That
infuriated Vice President Cheney.
And so so Cheney ordered the Pentagon to
create a new under secretary of
intelligence and the under secretary of
intelligence his sole role his sole
responsibility was to liaz with Ahmed
Chel. So, at the CIA, I remember getting
cables and saying, "Oh my god, did you
see this cable? It says that the Iraqis
have weapons of mass destruction. It has
the coordinates of where the weapons are
are located. It says who's in charge of
of the weapons and who has command and
control over the weapons. I've never
seen intelligence that was so crystal
clear like this. What's the source? And
it says in the source line, a reliable
source.
Well, who's the reliable source? It
turned out it was Ahmed Shelby. And so
we were getting this fake phony
intelligence that
just
supported war, a decision to go to war
and nothing else. Um, I will say
that it was the CIA's torture program
that also led to war with Iraq. Our
analysts knew that there was no
connection whatsoever between al-Qaeda
and the Iraqi government. I mean,
anybody who knew anything about the
Middle East or about history knew
that Osama bin Laden hated Saddam
Hussein as much as he hated the United
States. There was nothing Muslim about
Saddam Hussein. Nothing. He didn't know
the prayers, nothing. Yet, we allowed
this lie to take root inside the CIA
that there was some sort of cooperation
between al-Qaeda and uh the Iraqis in
the form of a highle meeting between
al-Qaeda and the Iraqi intelligence
service station chief in
Prague. We knew that that meeting never
took place, but under torture, one of
the al-Qaeda prisoners told us, "Oh,
yes, yes, it's a connection between
al-Qaeda and Iraq." and we use that as
one of the excuses to go to war knowing
that it was false. To answer the final
part of your question, and I hate to
sound cynical, I
apologize,
but the truth is after 9/11, we entered
into a
full-time wartime
economy. Millions of people got rich
because of 911. Millions of people got
rich because of the $2
trillion that we have spent on national
defense. And now it
is it is too late to turn that around.
If we were to stop spending that kind of
money in the military-industrial
complex, the economy would crash.
And as you as you alluded u to in the uh
in the question, we're also talking
about the Israeli economy here, right?
This isn't just the American economy,
but we prop up the Israeli economy at
the same time. I can't think of anything
more
wrong than the way the US government has
has conducted itself on military policy,
counterterrorism policy, security, and
policy toward Israel and by extension
Palestine since 9/11. We've been wrong
at every turn.
Building on that, John, you've spoken
powerfully about the revolving door also
so between intelligence agencies and
private contractors. So from where I sit
in a region shaped by these policies, it
often feels like war isn't just a
byproduct of profit but the plan der
deliverable. Oh yes. You've also warned
about the growing influence of Israeli
linked appointments inside US national
security roles. So let me ask you this.
Has US intelligence been structurally
captured by corporations and powerful
foreign allies to the point that even
its core doctrine is no longer fully its
own?
I I think the answer to that is
yes.
Um I
remember as early as the mid
1990s there were senior CIA
officers. You know what? I'll give you
one one example.
So
1994 uh there was a a senior CIA officer
what's called a division chief. So he's
in charge of all European operations,
European liaison operations, cooperation
with our European partners, etc. And he
retired after 30 32 years at the CIA. He
didn't know what to do with himself in
retirement because he was only in his
early 50s. So he still had 30 years
ahead of him that he could do something.
And so he created a small company that
was located about three kilometers, four
kilometers from the CIA's headquarters.
And really he he set it up as a place
where his friends when they retired
could also come and they would play tavi
and they would drink coffee and tell
stories and have a fun time and then
maybe they would get a government
contract.
He's now a
billionaire because just as this
company got to the point where it knew
what it was doing in federal
contracting, 9/11 came and everybody in
the company already had a security
clearance because they had all come from
the CIA and they had all been in the
senior intelligence service. So he paid
his friends with shares of the company.
The company was sold for something like
10 billion dollars to
IBM and now it's one of the largest
government contractors in the world.
What company? Everybody got rich. What's
the name of it? I'm sorry. What's the
name of it? It's called Abraasis. A
Braxus Corporation. Most of us haven't
heard of it. No. No. And you you
probably wouldn't even if you lived here
in the Washington area because it
operated very quietly. It was a
clandestine uh company. Everybody had
security clearances. Everybody had
experience in the CIA or in the Pentagon
or NSA and they just got lucky. Well,
that's actually kind of typical of the
way things have happened since 9/11. And
then you
mentioned, yeah, I'm going to call it
the Israeli infiltration of the of the
American government. And I I'll address
that from a different angle. On my very
first day at the CIA, and I'm talking 35
and a half years
ago, my very first day, all of the new
hires had a briefing by the CIA's direct
director of security. And he came in, he
said, "Welcome to the
CIA. There is an issue called counter
inelligence. That's very important. You
have to pay attention to this." And it
was little things. don't eat at
restaurants near the CIA because the
Russians assume that's where we eat and
so the places are full of
KGB, things like that. But he gave he
gave a talk on activist
counterintelligence
threats. He said that in the Israeli
embassy in Washington, there were two
what are called declared officers.
There's one Mossad officer and one
Shinbet officer. And when I say
declared, I mean that the Israeli
government has said these are officers
from Mossad and Shinbet. So you know who
they are and they're here to work with
you. He said there
are 187
undeclared Israeli intelligence
officers.
187 spread all across the United States,
stealing secrets from American military
contractors. Now, that's just
Israel. Think about the Russians, the
Chinese, the French, the
Cubans, you name it. We have more spies
here in Washington than any other city
on the planet. And it's something that
is just overwhelming. Now, with the
Israelis, one of the things that has
always bothered CIA officers, especially
CIA leaders, is that we give the
Israelis everything. We give them
everything they want, but they always
think that we're holding out on them.
And so, they try to steal it. Steal it
and then just compare what they were
able to steal with what we gave them. No
trust.
No, it's an ugly relationship. I think
it's more no trust from their part to
you. I I I don't think that the
Americans are actually spy actively
spying on the Israelis as they are. No,
I can tell you definitively that we are
not. No. No.
No. The Israelis sure spy on us.
Yeah. And it's supposed to be the
strongest partnership in the world. We
just like in a marriage, you know, there
should be trust. Well, when there's no
trust from the one side, but the other
side is disillusioned that there is. And
it's actually also feeding the other
side. And you're supporting their
economy, not just providing them with
arms, but financially also supporting
to to the tune of billions of dollars
every year. You know, the Israelis the
Israelis give their citizens or Israeli
refugees things that American citizens
and American refugees could only dream
about. Free apartments, free furniture,
subsidized jobs. We would love to have
things like that, but we use American
taxpayer money so that Israelis can have
things like that.
Yeah, it's outrageous. Let's go to
another pressing question. Um that's in
the region here where I live close by
where anyway it's it it has to do with
Iran. In your view, is the US public
ever truly at risk of of waking up to a
war with Iran? Or is the military
posturing under Trump more about
performative leverage aimed at managing
allies like Israel who demand perpetual
confrontation?
Oh, I'm I'm glad you used the word
demand. In my experience at the CIA and
at the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee after the CIA, literally every
Israeli prime minister, literally
everyone has asked the United States to
bomb Iran. Everyone. Benjamin Netanyahu
does not come to the United States
without first asking whoever happens to
be president to bomb Iran every
time. Um, and thank God that we have
said no every time. Now, Donald Trump,
of course, is a wild card. We don't know
what he's going to do. I don't think he
knows what he's going to do when he
wakes up in the morning. It changes
every day. But I think the the simple
answer to your question is no. I don't
think that there's a danger of a US war
with Iran. I think there is a very great
danger of an Israeli war with Iran. And
this would be a war of choice because
the Israelis see Iran as an existential
threat. Um it's
not. Iran has no nuclear uh weapons and
even if they had a nuclear weapon, they
have no delivery system to launch a
nuclear uh weapon against the Israelis.
The Israelis certainly have many many
nuclear
weapons. But uh but this would be a war
of choice and the choice would come from
Israel.
Now, call me
crazy, but I've been thinking about this
a lot. In the in the 1970s, we used to
have this phrase, only Nixon could go to
China, right? Richard Nixon, when he was
president, before he was president, was
the most
anti-China, anti-communist elected
official in America. And he ended up
going to China and making peace with the
Chinese and opening diplomatic relations
with the Chinese. And he changed
American foreign policy. And I'm
wondering if we're in a position now
where only Trump could go to
Iran. The reason I say that is I have
friends who work in the White House. I
have friends who are in daily contact
with Donald Trump and they say that
Trump is obsessed with winning the Nobel
Peace Prize. He hates that Barack Obama
got a Nobel Peace Prize. He didn't
deserve one, but they gave him one. And
Trump wants one, too. and he knows that
the only way he can do that is to make
peace. Now, he tried it with North Korea
and it fell through. But I think he's
trying it now with Iran.
And every day, literally every day, when
we get news from the US Iran
talks, we hear about some crazy position
that Trump has imposed on the
delegation. The Iranians can can
um can purify their uranium to 35%. Then
67%. But it can't go over 67. Okay, they
can do it. But then it has to be stored
in the Emirates. No, it won't be stored
in the Emirates. Everybody can do it.
And then it'll be stored in Oman. And
then Oman says, "We don't want this
enriched uranium." And then the Emiratis
say, "We'll take it." And the Iranians
say, "Well, we never agreed to any of
this. It's we're not going to send it
to." So it changes every single day.
It's like
craziness, but they're still talking.
What I've been doing is going to the
Iranian press releases at the end of
each round of talks, not the American
ones. I just ignore the American ones
because they don't make any sense. They
they change every day. The Iranian ones
are very well thought out. And I think
we get a real
a real view indication of what is
happening in those talks. Yes. And the
fact that the two two sides are still
meeting despite the fact that the US
changes policy almost every single
day tells me that that an agreement is
possible. Let's hope for the good of all
of us here. And that's right. Let's
hope. And it is going to make the
Israelis crazy. Mad. Mad. Crazy mad. Oh
my god. Mhm. We've had enough wars in
this region. Uh, John, I can tell you
that. Seriously. Right. Too much. How
many more people can you possibly kill?
1 million just in Iraq. And it's
generations upon generations of us who
are raised under this. That's right.
Even if we're not in the direct conflict
zone, we're always with this fear in the
back of our mind because if something
happens at this time, it's going to be
nuclear. Everyone's going to go. That's
right. And Cyprus is quite literally the
first place that everybody seeks to run.
Always which you know in in the event of
a of a serious conflict could crash the
criate economy. And and don't forget
we've only got like half of it. I mean
there's so much that we can say.
Exactly. So since you mentioned Cypress,
let's let's touch on Cypress because
it's always a soft spot for me. Um I'm
just going to give a brief historical
context also for some of the viewers who
might not uh know or have been following
the show. uh the past few months is that
Cyprus in 1974 was torn apart. Uh there
was a Turkish invasion in the summer of
1974 and the classified documents now
show that the US had fornowledge and
tacidly approved of the invasion. Um, as
a former CIA insider, I wanted to ask
you this directly because there's a dis
the classified transcription of a
recording between the US president at
the time and Henry Kissinger where the
uh secretary of state had acknowledged
to the president of Turkeykey's of of
knowledge of Turkeykey's plan to invade
and occupy 33% of the island and the
declassified recordings. Uh, you hear
him say, Kissinger say we can live with
that, Mr. President. But when US
ambassador to Greece Henry Taskca at the
time he opposed the coup from the Greek
uh Honta but he also very strongly tried
to stop the Turkish invasion. Washington
ignored Ambassador Taska and he later
resigned as a matter of conscience.
Decades later in a 1999 speech in
Athens, President Clinton admitted that
the US backed the Huna uh that set it
all in mo that set everything else then
in motion with Cypress being the victim.
He actually said that the United States
allowed its interests in prosecuting the
cold war to prevail over its interests
and I should say its obligation to
support democracy. This is what
President Clinton said, verbatative. So,
as someone who knows how US covered
policy works behind the scenes, John,
does Cyprus stand as one of the clearest
examples of a country sacrificed for
strategic interests? And if so, who
decides what a people's sovereignty is
worth? It's not an accident that Henry
Kissinger is known as the butcher of
Cyprus. It's not an accident that he's
known as the butcher of Cambodia and the
butcher of Chile.
uh that that was American foreign policy
in the in the 70s and frankly it hasn't
changed too too terribly much since the
1970s. I do blame the United States for
the division of Cypress. I don't think
the Turks would have had the guts to go
into Cyprus had they not received the
green light from the likes of Richard
Nixon and Henry Kissinger. And never
from those two has there had there ever
been an apology. They're both dead now.
I was actually in President Clinton's
speech in Athens when he made that
apology. I was serving in the American
embassy in Athens at the time. And it's
nice to make an apology, but what are
you going to do about it? What are you
going to do to back it up? The United
States still has an arms embargo on on
Cyprus. Cypress joined the European
Union and has a successful economy, but
a third of the country is occupied by
hostile foreign troops and the United
States isn't doing anything to to try to
push Turkey out. It's been half a
century and still how many how many
criates are missing and presumed dead
from that invasion? How many Americans
are still missing and presumed dead?
It's something like 11 or 15 or 17 or
something like that. This is a an
embarrassment of of American foreign
policy and it's an embarrassment of
historical
proportions. It it's it's a mistake, a
series of bad decisions that has
affected hundreds of thousands of lives
and has altered
history. And now the United States
prefers just to pretend that it hasn't
happened or okay, it happened. It's no
big deal. The Greeks and the Turks
aren't fighting in Cyprus now, so the
status quo is acceptable. It's not
acceptable. This is a hostile military
occupation of a sovereign
country. And I'll tell you, if I were
president,
um, I would come down much much harder
on the Turks than any American president
ever has. You know, there's there's one
there's one thing a professor of mine
mentioned one time. Wouldn't it be
wouldn't it be nice to throw the Turks
out of NATO? But we can't throw the
Turks out of NATO. Do you know why?
Because there is no mechanism by which
to throw a country out of NATO. It never
occurred to the creators of NATO in 1947
that they would ever need to throw a
country out. And so Turkey is perfectly
free to invade Cyprus, to invade
northern Iraq, to invade Syria and
Kurdistan, to to uh fight against the
Armenians and the Georgians and anybody
else that wants to do to threaten the
Greeks in the Aian. Exactly. To to to
destroy the the Greek Orthodox community
in in
Constantinople. And there's no price to
pay, nothing. We just take it. Impunity.
So there's literally nothing
positive on behalf of the United States
to say about this situation. Nothing.
It's an embarrassment of historic
proportions.
Thank you for that. And just to put it
in context for our audience to
understand, 5,000 Greek citrates were
killed during the invasion. 1% of the
Greek cate population at the time. That
that would contextually in for the US
amount to 3 million Americans killed in
an invasion. That's exactly right.
Lasted a month. Also a third of the
Greek cpriates me my family including
became refugees in our own country. A
third imagine 110 million Americans
being forcibly displaced from the
northern part of America to move to
become refugees in the north in their
own country in the southern part of
America. And that's right. When you say
a third of the island is under
occupation for the last 50 years, that's
the equivalent of California, Texas,
Florida, New York, Pennsylvania, Ohio,
Illinois, uh Georgia, North Carolina,
and Michigan combined under foreign
military occupation for half a century.
Now, if if if maybe that putting it into
that context and not just seeing this
tiny dot on the map being Cyprus, maybe
this makes it more tangible to people.
And I would add something. As horrible
as that is, what you just described, add
to it that Turkish settlers have taken
over uh land, property, houses in the
north that belong to Greek
criates. Imagine then if what you just
said about the United States took place
and then Russians moved in and took all
of our homes.
Yes. Uh um President Erdogan of Turkey
just paid an illegal visit to the
occupied part of Cyprus and he made some
preposterous and very um concerning
comments. Uh basically uh the population
now in the occupied parts, this was a
shock to us has is well over well over a
million. Most of them are actually not
Turkish shippers. are imported Turkish
settlers from the uh depths of Anatolia
and from the Turic states of of of
Central Asia and he has he has also
actually warned the Turkish criates that
we are actively going to Islamize
the so-called pseudo state that he said
that the Turks have set up there there
are more uh mosques uh uh per square
kilometer there than in any other part
of the world there more than 300 mosques
and uh they are continuously building
mosques and he told the Turkish criates
if you don't like the Islamization road
that we're taking here you can pack up
and go join your
your the Greek separates in the south.
So this is very concerning what you're
saying. It's um cultural heritage being
lost. It's not just that the the lives
that were lost at the time and the
displacement. It's an it's a demographic
demographic and cultural annihilation of
3,200 years of of Greek uh and
hellenistic presence on the island and
the Turkish ship once again are a
minority and they're being threatened
and that if you don't like what's
happening here you cannot leave.
You know for the very first time in my
life two weeks ago I met a Turkish
criate in New York. Oh they're fine. And
I said to him, I said, "Turkish criate."
I said, 'You know what? I've never met a
Turkish criate. And uh I said, "What
what made you come to New York?" And he
said, "What? I was going to stay in
Northern Cyprus?" "No, thank you." He
said, "It's all Turks." And he said,
"I'm a criate." The Turkish criates, he
told me, and and you can tell me if this
is true. He said, "We consider ourselves
criates." It's true. We don't consider
ourselves Turks. these Turks moving in
from Anatolia, they consider themselves
Turks to Turkify Cyprus. It's exactly
what he said that's not us. It's true.
Exactly. It's a crime against humanity.
It is. And um the Western world is just
um he made these very these threatening
comments. He wants to join the EU and uh
they are just airbrushing it. No one
dares you know even criticize Erdogan
from the west. No, no, no. They don't
they don't even dare crit. Even in
Turkey, they don't dare criticize him
because he'll kill them or jail them.
Yes. We see what's happening. And then
you're done. We see what's happening.
Yes. He's he's a dictator. They can call
it a democracy all they want, but he's a
dictator. Yes. So, and he's an
expansionist dictator. Oh, yes. With the
blue homeland doctrine that he has in
mind and his new Ottoman aspirations.
We had we had a an episode about that uh
the other day and um we put it all out
in the open and with I hope if people
want to see it again we're going to
provide a link in the description box.
But you're talking about you know why
why aren't they putting arms uh arms
embargo on Turkey. They don't even put
out statements that condemn him for what
he's doing it and anyway let's close
this off John because I've taken much of
your time. I'd like for you to share a
few words about what you're working on
now. I know you have a new book on the
way and beyond your work as a journalist
and a speaker, you're also a
screenwriter with credits on films like
Kill the Messenger. So, you've got the
CIA declassified series on Unified TV
and some exciting YouTube projects as
well. What should we be watching next
from you? Oh, thank you so much for
asking. I have two podcasts on on
YouTube right now. One is called uh Deep
Focus with John Kuryaku. The other one
is called uh DProgram. DProgram is kind
of a news recap uh uh podcast and Deep
Focus I have individual subjects that
that I interview just like you and I did
and we go deeper into these issues.
Unified TV um carries my TV show CIA
Declassified. It's a it's a an
internet-based TV network, and we take
declassified CIA documents, like the
documents related to Cyprus, for
example, and we tell these historical
stories based on what the CIA was saying
at the time. And um yeah, I have my
eighth book coming out in a couple of
weeks and um and doing a lot in
Hollywood. I try to I try to stay as
active as as possible in Hollywood. I I
sold the rights to my first book um to a
production company that wants to make it
into a film soon. And um and I sold a
script just two weeks ago. So, a little
bit here, a little bit there, and I can
put together a bit later. Which one of
the What was the book's title? The first
book was it the what about The first
book was The Reluctant Spy, My Secret
Life in the CIA's War on Terror. Great.
Great. It's going to be it's going to be
turned into a movie. That's fantastic.
Thank you so much, John. Thank you for
your time, your cander, and your
courage. In an age of disinformation,
few voices can speak to the inner
workings of the intelligence world with
the clarity and firsthand insight that
you bring. So, I hope this conversation
has helped our audience see through the
fog to better understand how truth is
buried, how power operates, and what it
costs to challenge the national security
machine from the inside.
Thank you so much. This channel depends
on you. So, if you file found this
interview interesting, hit like, drop a
comment, and subscribe. Don't forget
also to tap that notification bell, or
else you're going to miss on new drops.
As always, stay informed, stay
questioning, and stay unfiltered.
[Music]